hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Aaron Foss founder of
Nomo Robo an app that stops annoying
Robo calls and spam texts Forever on the
podcast I talk with Aaron about the
ultimate premium strategy making lowrisk
Bets with potentially asymmetrical
outcomes and how Aaron bounced back
after almost running out of money hey
Aaron thanks so much for joining us on
the podcast today oh my pleasure thanks
for having me I'm super excited to share
my story with all the sub Club listeners
awesome and it is quite a story so I
launched my first app back in 2008 and
it feels like every two or three years
there was a think piece about the end of
apps and it was 2010 was the end of apps
and 2012 was the end of apps and 2016
was the end of abs and in this time span
after multiple pundits have declared the
end of ABS you went from idea to
launching an app to exiting at over
eight figures and it's such a cool story
so I want to start digging in by
painting the picture of the assets you
had in place that allowed you to take
advantage and to have an advantage in
building Nomo Robo so what were you
doing before you started Nomo Robo that
kind of gave you those building blocks
to then build this company when I got
the idea for nomobo I was actually
between companies there's a lot of
people that are between jobs when
they're unemployed when you've just sold
one of your companies and then you're
trying to figure out your next adventure
that was the spot that I was in and I
love leaving it up to the universe to
push me in the right direction and I was
reading TechCrunch one day and there was
this robocall Challenge from the FTC and
I just got interested in that and that
is how it all started that's awesome and
before that though so you're actually a
programmer but then also have an NBA
have started multiple companies so you
kind of had this entrepreneurial base
where while you were waiting for the
universe to push you a direction you
actually had some experience some
Foundation behind that right yeah and I
knew what made me cranky and what I
didn't like uh so exactly I got my
undergrad was in information technology
and then I bolted on my MBA went to
school in Rochester New York at RIT and
I thought I wanted to work at a big
company to this day I don't know why but
like just seemed like the right idea and
even back then my mom was like you know
you're going to make a terrible employee
I was like okay well let's see what
happens right I was a bad employee for
all the right reasons right I worked for
basically Motorola it was a company
called symbol it was acquired by
Motorola and I was building really cool
stuff really quickly and that was just
like incompatible with big companies my
401k vested on what week 52 like day 365
I was there for two more weeks and then
I started my own thing I started a
consulting company and then one thing
led to another other where I had a few
successes and failures in the startup
World until I finally kind of hit my
stride in roughly around 2011 yeah
that's awesome and everybody has
different advantages I think there's
folks listening to this podcast who are
a marketer at a bigger app or they're in
product or they're you know have
different experience life experience
business experience entrepreneurial
drive whatever it is and putting those
building blocks together and going for
it is what it takes to build a company
like no Robo so it's really cool to see
that story of how you had this
entrepreneurial journey and pushed you
into creating the app so then let's talk
through the
FTC contest so you saw on Tech crunch
the FCC wanted to solve rooc calls
where'd you get from there I had been
building telepan apps for years I was
one of the first adopters of twilio when
I saw twio I still remember this first
time I saw it it was like holy crap I've
been looking to be able to hook my code
into the phone system system and it's
always been impossible and twilio makes
this simple I got like a modem for my
bar mitzvah like I was on bbs's in the
90s like I go way way way back I saw
twilio I jumped on it just built a whole
bunch of stuff with our user group here
in New York City I entered Tech crunch
disrupt hackathons and everything that I
built had some sort of communication
telefony SMS something like that so I
had a lot of experience in that area but
I had never built anything commercial
right so FTC this is what's weird about
it is that like the FTC is the
government agency that is tasked with
stopping robocalls and they put out this
competition it was a crowdsourced
competition which were 13 years ago it
was really popular have a crowdsourced
contest and a competition and get the
best ideas from people who ordinarily
wouldn't be in this industry and that's
exactly what happened they put up
$5,000 800 people entered and they
picked me and another guy we split the
prize what's interesting too is that
that was super controversial back then
there was so much negativity with like
wait you're the FTC and you're given 50
Grand to someone to solve the problem
that you're tested with solving but we
in the industry and and they understood
that if it wasn't for that not that I
needed the money but that was the cool
there was a big prize and like then I
became aware of how big this problem was
and then I was you know incentivized to
try and solve it well things you and I
have talked about before is how Nomar
Robo is ultimately the compounding of
thousands of small decisions and a few
large decisions and this is one of those
large decisions but it was also like a
super low-risk decision right you didn't
have to put hundreds of thousands of
dollars on the line you didn't have to
quit a job because you put yourself in a
position where it was a low-risk
opportunity so yeah tell me more about
jumping head first into that contest and
how long it did take you to pull
something together I love things where
the risk and reward is out of balance
where obviously the risk is low and the
reward is high you don't want it the
other way that's not it but that kind of
framing as like why wouldn't you at
least take the shot so as I mentioned
before that I was with a company called
Sor and we went through Tech Stars in
2011 so it's just a little bit earlier
and what I learned in Tech Stars was
your technology is great and wonderful
and the product is great and wonderful
and all your team and all those other
pieces what's really important is how
you pitch that idea to people it's going
to be if you're pitching to investors if
you're pitching to potential hires if
you're pitching to Partners investors
whoever it may be getting that idea
across and so I knew I had a
technological solution and thinking back
the rules were basically impossible it
had to work on mobile it had to work on
landlines had to be easy to use it had
to work no false positives you know so
it knocked out apps this is the thing
that a lot of people forget about is
right we're known for our one of the top
apps in the App Store now but when I
started the company building apps like
this was impossible and want say like
illegal but Apple prevented it you know
this is Apple's world we just live in it
so how insane is that to start an app
company building an app that is against
App Store rule we couldn't do it but
what I could do is on the landline side
I had this idea on how to use sim ring
which is one of those little dark
corners of Telecom and it's a feature
that everybody knows voicemail and way
calling and all those other pieces but
siming basically let us put a phone
number was powered by twio people would
be able to put it into their siming list
and then we would basically get a copy
of the call as the call came into their
house it would also ring on our server
and that way we could do all the
analytics so I was able to pitch that
and that really was the key if you read
the competition guidelines and you read
between the lines you could see that the
FTC wanted something that went around
the carriers it couldn't have carrier
cooperation because the carriers weren't
incentivized to fix this so my idea of
being able to go to the consumer
directly have them do something
relatively simple and then get robocall
protection that's ultimately why they
picked and that's actually it's
interesting but the second person that
we split with had a better algorithm I
basically had no algorithm at that point
I was like we'll figure out how to do
that but the key was almost like this
distribution this go to market this how
are we going to get to Consumers and
that other person or I guess 799 other
people people just didn't have anything
that was good enough to win yeah and so
sharing that quote idea you came up with
an Innovative solution using existing
technology getting around the carriers
and then you talked about it on stage
how did you build a company on an idea
that was already out in the public
before you even launched what's really
interesting about this competition right
I won and they also picked another
winner he had a better algorithm I had a
better way of getting to the consumer
thing is he didn't want anybody to quote
steal his idea so when the press
conference came right they invited us
both down to DC to be in the press
conference he didn't want anybody to
steal his idea he didn't want to talk
publicly I jumped on a train and was
there as quickly as I could get there
and so it's a giant press conference
about a giant problem from a giant
organization from a giant government and
there's one guy there so there's all
these cameras so I'm doing interviews
with CNN and Fox Business News and
everybody I would just talk to everybody
do you have time to talk to the New York
Times I'll stay here all day and I'll
talk to everyone did I go into the
technical details no did I talk about
simmering and this no but using a part
of the phone system it's going to be
launched and again like nobody ever
heard from the other guy again I don't
know what he did yeah so it's
interesting how you did share and the
other guy didn't but part of the value
in Sharing was that you got a ton of
attention that you wouldn't have
otherwise gotten I know you eventually
created a sign up page did you have that
before you went to this press conference
were you shouting from the rooftops go
to nomorobo.com and join the wait list
yep that's the simple answer right I
knew that that was an opportunity like
the amount of we call it like earned
media now but I was just like yeah I got
to get as many people and capture their
information as much as I can because I
knew that that was my cheat code that
was the thing that I had that no one
else did so even when I entered the
competition I put together a video
nobody else put together a video I built
a prototype maybe some people made
prototypes most people made like a
business plan like a 30 page description
of what they were doing mine was a
one-pager maybe it was two talked about
the general technical pieces it was all
the source code the database schema a
video demon literally at this desk right
this desk what I'm sitting at right here
is where I built it and then I just sent
it on over there and still remember the
day I was sitting right here and I'm
coding and my part of my brain just came
up with the name it was just thinking
about like no more Robo call like oh
call it no more Robo and I checked the
domain was there I registered it cool
went moved on and maybe that's the other
part too is for this competition right I
named it something catchy no mo Robo no
more robocalls this other guy had it was
a white list gy list Blacklist wayy the
name was like 17 letters and everything
and it just wasn't catchy whereas for me
they' be like and his idea noobo cool
that's what got it go to nomorobo.com it
was the video and a little box that said
put in your email and we'll let you know
when we launch and by the time I
launched I had over 30,000 people that
had given me their email address right
for free just that was what I used as an
analog for do people want this right it
wasn't earning Revenue I wasn't but like
every day that I was seeing more and
more email addresses coming in I knew
that this was a big problem that needed
to be solved I couldn't not do that yeah
and that's the thing is like there are
ideas that you want to have a big launch
and so you you want to keep some things
close to the chest but when you get
something out there you validate whether
you should spend the next 6 months of
your life building this or not and it's
just such a great story that you shared
all of that and instead of just getting
ripped off it actually was this lever
for you to then launch from a much
stronger position and again another
thing that you told me in the past was
like if the idea was that easy to just
rip off you probably don't have a
business anyway so that's exactly and
you know what's funny about that like so
the way use simring in my opinion even
to this day there was only one way to
win that competition was by using
simring so when I'm writing the code I
figured that there was going to be like
five other people that were going to
come up with this because when I looked
at the problem there was only one
solution and it was using simmering that
was what I was most worried about that I
was just entering with something that
everybody else did no as a matter of
fact I talked to the CTO of the FTC
afterwards he was the guy that was in
charge of this whole competition and
they looked looked at all 800 entries
and when mine came up he basically say
he's like this can't be true he's like
cuz if this was so true it looks easy
everybody would be doing it and this is
the story he told me right he called his
friend at AT&T and he like I don't know
there's this guy in the competition and
using Sim ring and he's like that
wouldn't work right and the guy went
actually that would he went no he hung
up the phone called up another guy and
like come on this he's like when the
second guy told me like actually that's
just like stupid enough to work he like
we knew that you had won at that point
but if I hadn't done that I don't know
where we would be okay so you win the
contest you get a bunch of press now you
actually got to build the thing did you
raise $10 million hire a huge team and
hit the ground running or what' you do
well so first part I was also doing some
Consulting and so I had to wind those
down okay I got to get some Breathing
Room cool great tell everybody like last
train and everything I won the
competition in April of 2013 and then I
got invited to speak in front of
Congress in July which was okay this is
an opportunity I've now testified in
fromont of Congress three times so like
if anybody has any questions on what to
do give me a call I've done it a lot as
a fact that the last time I did it I was
sitting in the chair that Mark
Zuckerberg sat in just a few weeks
before you know his did not go nearly as
well as mine did but that became more
media that became a bigger part of the
story and I was already building it if
you look at my testimony go on C-Span
you can see I say I'm like and I already
have 3,000 people who have signed up
which I thought was great right in a
couple months getting 3,000 as I
mentioned before right when it launched
on October 1st that had over 30,000 but
no what I figured was okay I got 25
Grand from this competition I don't know
maybe that'll last me a day maybe it'll
last me a year I don't know and I always
figured that that was an economic thing
my only expense at that point was twilio
and it was the biggest one because the
way my idea worked is we have to answer
every robocall and then hang up on it so
I know everybody oh it's free calls and
everything like that yes but at volume
and things so when I flip the switch on
it's the stand Story the email servers
got shut down cuz they thought we were
spamming so many invites and the Ser
like I'm I'm running I'm jumping from
one foot to the other and everything but
that after that first week did the
numbers I'm like I'm gonna run out of
money in six weeks so turning to twilio
again I know Jeff I know all those guys
I was like what can we do we started
negotiating that I figured out what can
happen and then we opened up a
convertible note but it was friends and
family it was like my mom my stepfather
a couple of guys that I knew that had
successful exits but it was very very
small let's see what happens cuz there
was no business model at that moment
maybe is the really important part is in
order to stop robocalls you need a lot
of data but in order to get the data you
already need to be stopping rooc calls
so none of that data existed so this is
the other part like I needed to prime
the pump somehow giving away the
robocall data would get me the real time
data that I needed I needed something
else I was talking to the FTC about this
and telling them about this problem and
they said well would it help if you got
five years worth of all of our do not
call complaint data
I go that would be really helpful and
because again I don't know anything
they're like well if you foyer it we are
going to be obligated to send it to you
I said I will go and do that so day one
I got the CD ROM in the mail and I
crunched through it kind of ridiculous
looking back at it right the false
positives like it was blocking stuff it
wasn't supposed to and whatever but it
was enough to start and then give away
the roboco blocking on the landline side
which arguably has much less value than
the mobile side but again I didn't even
know how we were going to do mobile but
I just needed time to basically figure
it out I figured okay we'll monetize
this somehow we just got to go and get
this data get people putting their
number in their simmering list and I'll
figure the rest out that's why yeah if I
went and try to raise you know $10
million what are you going to do with it
I have no idea so it was just enough to
keep the business running and our first
kpi right was only one and I recommend
this for all entrepreneurs a startup can
do like one thing barely ours was was
robocalls block cuz that meant that it
was working people were signing up
people trusted it it was growing and
that kind of thing so that was the only
metric that we did and then everything
that needed to block more rooc calls
when I needed more money that was where
it came in right so you built it all
yourself so you used that engineering
background and built it all still to
this day like the devs Now call it like
iron code there's like initial Cod and I
built all the website literally every
single thing was written by me that's
incredible so then that fall you launch
on the web to block
landlines and you're not making any
money you raise a little to like keep
the lights on keep yourself fed keep the
office AC going when did you first start
thinking okay we're GNA monetize this
and this is how we're going to monetize
it the Turning Point really came with
iOS 10 so Apple said devs can now build
apps that block calls one of my
investors actually had a house on fire
Island and we were walking to it and I
just happened to mention I was like yeah
Apple iOS 10 is allowing it okay so then
you're going to have to build it I went
damn yeah you're right it was like one
of those I like okay okay okay now to
that point well you're giving away the
landline give away the mobile but I was
like no we got to monetize this at some
point and that's really the turning
point so that's the part that's
interesting and I think maybe to your
listeners you're on sub club right we
were one of the first robocall blocking
apps in the App Store but more
importantly we were one of the first
apps that use subscriptions everything
was I AP in app purchases and everything
I don't know if we were the first but
easily one of the first five because I
knew that that's how we needed to
monetize it two bucks a month or $20 for
the year but at least that way and it
was just using the same Tech all the
data right it's all the same data that
we're just getting it in different ways
and that was the inflection point where
once the mobile app came in now all of a
sudden we had some API like Enterprise
deals we were selling queries and things
it brought in an amount of money but not
enough to be a viable business but when
Apple changed everything we were able to
sell direct to the consumer that's
really when it changed and I could talk
talk about the rest of it cuz it changed
a couple more times after that I wish I
would have in 2014 2015 said the only
real viable way to monetize a weather
app is via subscription and been a
little bit earlier to that bandw wagon
there was consumer push back during
those early days people were used to
free and cheap and paid up front apps
it's interesting how the cost probably
helped force that decision when you have
ongoing costs like the better it works
the more calls it blocks the more calls
you get the more expensive it is for you
to run this service like it's just not
practical to do this in upfront payments
or any of the other really models
available I mean you could have like
sold bundles of calls and it would have
been a mess and there's just so many
ways that Apple opening up subscriptions
as they did in 2016 when you started
doing it allowed an app like no more
Robo to exist like the platforms because
of the limitation on business models and
I think things have improved with
subscription and as much as a bull as I
am on subscription specifically I still
wish Apple would allow other options
like upgrade pricing like there's so
many other business models that's a
whole another conversation but it's cool
that the timing of you kind of landing
on an app coincided both with you
understanding that I need to monetize
via subscription Apple allowing it and
then even iOS 10 it was like kind of a
perfect storm of technology and
monetization to launch at the right time
one other piece too is our price point
and everybody complains about the Apple
tax but on a $1.99 a month we were
actually getting a better deal if we had
to go and get off thees shelf kind of
pricing and we had to run it ourselves I
actually did the math I'm like actually
apple is cheaper yeah for that and so
everybody was fighting me on all two
bucks a month how you going to do this
what about that I saw it very simply or
maybe I just didn't know any better I
was like here's a service that you need
constant updating every 15 minutes two
bucks you're going to pay for we have
the ability to do sub descriptions
easily we don't need to go and craft all
this from our we just latch on to Apple
and then we just collect checks and that
was the beginning part if we want to
call it in phase one that was the
beginning of the company and when the
light at the end of the tunnel like well
there was a light right if you're
walking down that tunnel with a
flashlight and looking and looking and
looking that was the first point I was
like there was a glimmer like I always
knew I was on the path or a path and I
knew kind of the general direction but
that finally was like wait wait here it
is here's the answer so again talking
about like all these small and big
decisions that are compounding over time
you've won the contest you've built up
this email list you've launched on the
web you've got users you've got people's
attention how did you launch the app was
it just a massive Splash by that time
did you have 100,000 emails or in 2016
when you launched the app what did that
look like I'm not a big fan of big bang
launches maybe because I just got burned
that one time there's so many things
that can go wrong so every launch we've
had I don't want to say it's been like a
soft launch but it's ready when it's
ready and then we push it out and then
on our end like we've never done any
paid acquisition is just organic and
it's also leveraging what we already had
so we had all of these landline people
that we were covering we had their email
address they loved it on their landline
so when you send somebody an email and
you're like hey you love it on your
landline why don't you try it on mobile
this is also probably pretty important
too is from the very beginning we built
in the free trial I didn't want this to
be a premium we gave a twoe free trial
because we wanted people to try you may
not get a robo call today or tomorrow
what but by two weeks in you're going to
know so in so many words like giving
people more than they expected it made
it very easy like just push the button
try it on out and even said like if it
doesn't work for you totally cool just
cancel your subscription so those things
just made everything easier if we had
charged whatever $7,000 or we gave a
three minute trial or we need you to
literally take out your credit card
write it on down send us a check all
these things that are just putting freak
in I think that's why it was really
successful we just didn't I want to say
we didn't have to work hard obviously
really really hard but we didn't have to
work hard convincing people that the
demand was there the problem is there
people were screaming for a solution and
we had already proved ourselves so that
part yeah we put it into the App Store
and we might have sent a press release I
don't even remember went to the
reporters that had been covering it for
a while hey we got this new thing they
were able to oh cool that's new let's go
and get that out there using it and then
that train that just started chugging
along that flywheel started moving and
then we just kept on adding more fuel to
that fire so the launch you said you
kind of soft launched it did you get
like tens of thousands of downloads
hundreds of downloads and at what point
did you really ratchet up to SP it did a
lot of press come in right away or
you're saying you launched it and kind
of waited two or three weeks make sure
everything was going good send out a few
emails check in and then you told the
press and sent the big email blast yeah
basically we launched it made sure that
you know we had to obviously get some
bug fixes and all those other things
then once it was ready yeah I would just
write to a reporter and hey herb I know
you wrote about this all the last time
go in we grew but and maybe this is a
flaw of mine but I build something and
then I'm on to the next thing and like I
don't even look back so many people are
like looking at the analytics and this
and that all I figure is okay that's
quote unquote done for now it's launched
cool on to the next one I'm not a big
goals Setter like that I don't think
goals work and deadlines and things I
like systems and things and things just
take as long as they do and then when
they're ready they get pushed out and
literally that worked we talked about
the press and then we were on to our
Android version cool okay guys let's do
it again build out that whole thing and
you have to find the team and everything
and then what's that done but just keep
on moving so I couldn't even really tell
you I just I want say I stopped looking
I had it in my board deck and everything
like that but it was just like okay this
is making money this is working let's
fix it keep on moving forward what's the
next thing what's the next thing and not
in a o squirrel or shiny new thing but
just like what's the next thing that we
need to do and again I want to give away
the ending but that's how also I knew
that the company was kind of ready for
acquisition when my work was done
everything obviously can be better and
better and better but I kind of got to
the end of what I'm really good at what
makes me special what makes like it
needed to grow up it needed to graduate
and that was a thing that I had a lot of
time wrestling with but ultimately that
was the right decision at what point in
this story did you start hiring you're a
lone wolf did you hire to build the app
and how did you think about that hiring
process I know we've had other solo
developers on the podcast like card
pointers Emanuel ciser and the slopes
app Curtis Herbert I don't think Emanuel
has actually hired somebody yet I know
Curtis now I think has two employees but
when you're a solo it is kind of a big
leap like it's important to really think
through when and who to hire so how did
you think through that process of
growing the team around you couple of
pieces first one was it was a lot of
work obviously and doing everything so
the first piece that I'm like okay and I
love customer support I love talking to
all the customers and being right there
but like I can't talk to every customer
and do this and do that so the first
piece that I thought is okay I can break
off off customer support as it turns out
it was a guy that I was in tech stars
with he was a hack star and the company
that he worked for had folded so he was
kind of like looking for opportunities
and in that case it was just as a
contractor he's like do you have
anything to do I'm like we need to set
up customer support he's like oh I set
up Zen desk and like oh awesome can you
do that for me so we that might have set
the tone for working with a lot of
independent contractors it wasn't just
because you know I want to say like race
to the bottom cheapest I actually found
that some of the best people you can't
hire them you can contract with them
they may be here and like looking at
that opportunity so he set me up he did
all the customer support then he went
and got another job and he's like good
news bad news bad news is I'm not
Consulting anymore the good news is my
brother is graduating from college and
he's really good at the stuff also cool
he took over and was able to build the
entire thing and now he's actually the
product manager worked his way up I did
the same thing on the technical side
okay I can write all the code but I
could use some help and this is funny is
that I've never like put out a job
application or done interviews or
anything like that everything was
written in LL and PHP and there was
Scott Jason Gilmore very good friend of
mine even to this day he wrote basically
some of the original books on Lille and
he was offering you give buy the books
and whatever I was like I want to be a
better developer I just saw him from his
offering so I go and buy it and it's
like well you can get the book for x and
the book and the videos for $100 or the
book The videos and a 1-hour
consultation for like 200 bucks I get it
now it was like lead gen right we jumped
on and we talked and we really hit it
off and I just want to learn some more
I'm like do you do Consulting and he was
like yeah I can and like we worked
together for years from that we just
kind of like found each other it wasn't
now hiring or doing that seems to be the
way that we've grown the team and I can
give you seven other examples of how
that happened no that's really cool for
a lot of entrepreneurs that's how you
have to think it's like when you're at
110% what's the 20% you can carve out to
give yourself just a little bit more
breathing rim to work on those higher
leverage things and then you start
working on those higher leverage things
and you get back to 110% capacity and
you're like okay now I got to carve out
another 20 or 30% to free myself up the
ad hoc bootstrap very Scrappy starting
with contractors I think it's just a
such a smart way to operate in the
mobile space I think it's been
interesting and will continue to be
interesting seeing companies like Nomo
Robo get built and have fantastic exits
when the narrative around VC like do you
go raise a million that just sets a
whole different set of priorities a
different set of expectations and yeah
you can then go hire somebody full-time
hire a whole team and build out the team
but sometimes doing that doesn't help
you go faster and being Scrappy and
hiring as needed working with good
contractors is a great way to build a
business and own more of that business
in the end yeah what I found very early
on you just don't know what to focus on
as a startup oh we can do this we can do
that we can do this if you then have
unlimited resources right you're like oh
we'll just hire this person we'll hire
this person well now all of a sudden the
focus gets even less focused I don't
really have a methodology I've never
again worked with big teams or anything
but I just called like a hopper like my
job was to keep the developers Hopper
full and to manage what's important on
that and then their job was just to pop
out the thing on the top and sometimes
that thing on the top gets pushed down
because there's other things and
whatever and so like I have two time
frames it's now or later are we working
on it now cool let's do it or we're
working on it later sometimes later
never comes and then that feature just
wasn't important but knowing that here's
your resources and that's a constraint
that you're confined in that okay cool
what we got then that means we can't do
these three things we can do one of them
cool okay well let's run then do the
next one I say there's an infinite
amount of work because once you do
something we got to do and there's of
course bug fixes and those kinds of
things those obviously pop up to the top
I love that constraints just breed
creativity that's the way I like to
build a business yeah looking back over
the last decade VC has even said like
it's just a different game and I I don't
know what we're calling this here it's
Indie development or whatever but like
this is going to become the norm even
when I started like even remote
businesses weren't really popular my
board was like when are you going to buy
your own
servers yeah ex I laughed I was like
never yeah you just looked at me I was
like we don't do that anymore you just
get rack and Stat no that's not what I'm
going to use the money for that doesn't
make any of course I couldn't say that
but that's what I was thinking I was
like you just don't get it now aays I
think people are getting this I don't
know what this is but hopefully it'll
have something to be fair I think
there's times when the money can be an
accelerant but that's what you really
need to understand is like when will the
money actually be an accelerant and when
will it unfocus you as you put it like
when will it remove too many constraints
that where the constraints were actually
helping pull you in the right direction
you did end up raising money right what
was the total you ended up raising over
the course a little over it was two and
a quarter you did raise money but you
raised money along the way not like I
need a million dollars to even build
this thing out what was the thinking
behind when and how much you did end up
Rising so we basically did it in two
tranches right so the preed basically a
million and then a million in a quarter
and that was before safes existed and
everything it was a regular convertible
note but the first one I opened for half
a million but I raised I think 50 Grand
of that okay cool because it was rolling
okay let's see what that happens and
then I did the 250 and then we kind of
extended that when it got up to the
million that's when we did a raise and
then that got to profitability it was
just kind of on an as needed basis it
was like okay there's traction we're
moving the right direction we're not
going to go raise a ton of money we're
going to raise just as much as we need
to get to this next step and then you
just kind of slow rolled those raises
yeah and I never thought about it in
that way but yeah and like it's not one
of those things we didn't have to meet
any milestones and it wasn't adversarial
or anything like you'll get this when
you get that like this isn't like
training a dog or giving a treats to a
an animal but it was just like hey I
need this much cuz we have a lot of
assumptions that we have to go and test
and we don't know and the and so we
didn't even do any advertising cuz there
been no way to do it but I was able to
literally call or email all the main
reporters we did a lot with SEO and
organic so didn't have to budget for
that what do we need to budget for our
Telecom development folks and that was
how we just kept on growing that way and
then I'm glossing over it but we have
the White Knuckle right $944 in the bank
account story if you want to hear that
one too yeah know tell me that story
well I kind of gave it away but
basically we launched the mobile app but
as you know like there was a 14-day
trial and then there was 30 days from
Apple and then another 30 days and in
that time the investors were even say oh
you're going to run out of money and
that's when it got a little bit tense
and they would invest again but it was
under very very poor terms it was really
really bad and I literally just had to I
saw the way that this was going just the
timing had to be absolutely perfect and
I reached out to twilio and I was like
instead of net 30 can I get net 90 for 3
months I need a bit of a loan here
because of the whole thing and they were
like yeah absolutely right I went to the
bank I was able to get a line of credit
didn't need to touch into that but at
least I got that in case I needed so I
had backup plans in case things went
poorly and then there might have been
like oh we paid this bill a little bit
later and everything but literally $944
in the bank account was probably an OV
exaggeration because if you go and look
at all the bills that we owed but it
literally potentially to the day to the
minute to the whatever just coincided
that then those apple checks started
coming in then we were able to do it
then we went back down to normal terms
and then it just flew it really was but
it was a dangerous dangerous game that
even looking back I don't know how it
worked but I knew at that point the deal
that the investors were giving me was
untenable because they had backed me
into a corner basically if I took that I
basically would have had nothing even if
this thing got to be huge I would have
had nothing there was a zero chance of
me having anything at the end of that
and if I rolled the dice there was a
nonzero chance of having it so I was
like well rationally I got to roll the
dice and and it in that case pulled out
all the stops and it worked yeah the
scrappiness that's how you have to
operate right like back in 2008 I was in
the same position Apple's paying 33 days
after the close of the fiscal month is
tough in many circumstances I actually
after launching my apps I hit probably
very similar I don't have the exact
number in my head that I've remembered
all these years later but I ended up
selling my wife's car to keep going
until I got that first Apple payment so
it's like I knew the money was coming so
I just needed whatever it was like 30
days of runway for my wife and I to get
the bills paid and we sold her car and
we're like a onecar family for another
like five years just to keep the lights
on and stretch until that first payment
came in just before that story you kind
of glossed over a few things so you
didn't do paid marketing ever but talk
me through some of the things that you
did do from SEO to press let's go
through each of those individually what
you would consider the top three or four
group growth levers that you did put
effort into and probably even spent
money on contractors and other things
even if you didn't actually pay for ads
directly you spent on marketing you just
didn't pay for advertising so let's talk
through those key leverage points that
you unlocked in this journey the way I
look at it is your product is part of
your marketing so offering the free
landline blocking my twillo bill peaked
at like 120k a month it was pricey it
was always during political season cuz
that's when all the rooc I you may have
remembered there were one or two really
big elections in that time when just the
calls skyrocketed but because of that
it's like okay well then the next piece
is now we have everybody's email address
that we can then go and say Hey try out
these other pieces so that was really
huge second from the data that we were
able to build up we're able to do a lot
of organic and SEO so what happened so
in addition to the consumer calls that
are coming in we built a Honeypot so we
bought all of these old dirty numbers
from twilio and other carriers it grew
to over 300,000 lines of a honeypop but
we're never answering and recording the
consumer calls we're super privacy
conscious focused we got our start with
the FTC we can't touch that but on
company-owned phone lines we can do
whatever the hell we want so that
balance of using the consumer side to
figure out some of the data points then
sending it over to the Honeypot where
we're able to get recordings and more
data and then generating programmatic
SEO pages from that so one of the
thoughts that I kind of had was like
okay what happens now if you get a call
from an unknown number while it's
ringing you run over to Google and you
type it in and you hope that you can get
there right well let's just make landing
pages for every one of those phone
numbers so when you type it in it'll say
no Mor Robo and this is a scam call be
and when you clicked on it it would give
you the recording it would give you the
transcription and then it would say hey
block this and you know 7 million other
robocallers so all of that could have
been our organic side our marketing
budget but that's where I said this is a
really good use I would rather spend
$100,000 a month and block Robo calls
and then funnel that into something
usable on the SEO side rather than
$100,000 in an ad budget which maybe
that would work too I don't know but I
just felt that it was better to build
the product and then bring people
together when you're looking for you see
a phone number and that was the thing
maybe an ret it was like if you have a
different kind of app or whatever maybe
don't know the longtail keywords ours
were so
longtail it was just a number right a
10-digit number but it worked really
really well and that was like one of
those Moes that we built is that you
couldn't really compete against that
once we were there and we were offering
value on both sides and then saying hey
you want to go and do a trial again
night yes sure we took away all of the
friction and then it just made
everything so even the new acquirers
they're big into PID well that's just
going to make the paid better cool click
on it get your trial move on through and
if we had anything that increased
friction I don't think it would work
very well okay so number one you have
the freemium landline product that
you're upselling the mobile product to I
would consider landline free even to
this day you can't pay for it and
there's nothing you got you can't get
anything better it's just literally we
just protect your landline for free
that's awesome okay so you have this
totally free and I was saying premium
because for a lot of your customers I
would imagine they're using the landline
for free and they're using the mobile
app paid so it's a weird kind of Premium
and maybe this is another piece I left
this out but because we were offering it
for free the carriers came to us and
said can we tell people about it like
yeah so like literally I get a call at
the time it was Time Warner right now
spectrum they were coming to us because
they were like oh if we build this in
and then we can basically check off the
box that we're providing roboco blocking
yeah and we don't have to pay for it no
so literally in the control panels
there's one click access where they
would hit RPI send us the phone number
get it activated put the simmering
number into their whole thing and yeah
that was another huge channel that we
didn't have to pay for or we would have
needed to spin up the whole fdev
Division and work on these whole things
and again like we talking about 10,000
little things would they have done it if
we had not won the FTC competition
probably not would they have done it if
they couldn't try it out on their own
and seen it probably not each one of
those then they came to us and like how
do we do this cool let's just go and do
that and that started building that was
the free side but you're right all these
I guess you could technically say it's
part of a marketing budget yeah and this
is where I think a lot of people get
fremium wrong where when you're going to
offer a free product and not directly
monetize ideally now there are some
cases where you are just going to give
away value for totally free and maybe
not even have ads or whatever but
ideally when it's most synergistic when
it works the absolute best those premium
users are delivering value in some other
way it's like all Trails they're
suggesting new trails and tracking new
trails and correcting trails and part of
the community and like they're helping
build out the value that then all Trails
sells in the premium subscription and so
in your case it's fascinating that it
really is a form of freemium and what
you were doing was subsidizing the free
landline blocking because that gave you
so much data that then made the mobile
product that was paid so much better
such a fascinating end round of Premium
like it's not your standard fremium but
that's exactly what you're doing and
it's that perfect kind of synergistic
fremium free and premium are dangerous
games like if you do it free and premium
are user acquisition paths it's not a
revenue model necessarily it's a way of
acquiring customers so yeah looking at
it through that lens I always joke it's
like riding a unicycle juggling
chainsaws that are on fire if you do
something wrong you're dead but if it
works it's really impressive and if you
can reduce the risk of it not working
and again this defined in all these
different ways that seems to be the
theme but yes the 2023 we're looking at
it very differently people understand it
back then Instagram was six months maybe
a year old or something maybe it just
been acquired like Airbnb was still new
Uber was still like all shiny and new
and like everybody just looked at the
world differently it's like just give it
away give it away give it away that's
well other than being like a redot Chili
Pepper song Als so but it's just that
was the thing back then nowaday you just
can't do that you have to use those as
user acquisition channels and you have
to think about it as your in your
business as that it's not going to earn
you Revenue so how is it bringing you
value is it bringing you value through
data is it bringing you value through
Community is it bringing you value
through being an amplifier of Word of
Mouth how are those premium users
actually delivering business value and
if they're not this is a pretty big
question whether you should be operating
premium you nailed it that V word right
value I mean so many people think of
again Revenue expenses but you're
exactly right value comes in a lot of
different ways and so as long as you
know in your company where they're
creating so again in our case the
landline was value oh dollars yeah but
there's other ones what about data o
yeah that we can then monetize you're
exactly right you have to look at
everything as far as what kind of value
are you gaining or giving or all those
put together okay so landline freemium
strategy is number one number two was
programmatic SEO which was a brilliant
move number three I'm going to give you
number three press how did you manage
press and other earned media getting
featured by Apple and that sort of thing
I'm a one trick pony man it's a good
trick right what do I do right I look at
it and I go okay news wants new stuff
and look some of the competitors in the
robocall space always just put out data
and analytics right 8 billion robocall I
always just thought that was like cheesy
I still do it's like yes robocalls are
bad that story's been told a thousand
times but you know what story hasn't
been told hey what's this robocall
that's coming in right now what's going
into Seattle what are the robocalls that
are hitting Austin and because we had
all this analytics from the consumer
side right we had on every carrier every
major VI carrier across the United
States and we had our Honeypot that can
go and catch record and transcribe them
and everything so we could go to a
reporter who was in Austin and say hey
here are the top scams that are hitting
Austin right now along with audio now
we'll talk about it well that got people
because again it wants to be local and
things we got national news stories
right we're on NBC Nightly News all that
and it was all because of if you're just
giving data okay that's great you know
according to blah blah blah you're
getting all this with us they were like
well now we want to see how do you get
this let's hear it let's play so all of
that and this was all on our landing
pages right but all of that just
leveraging that if you give a reporter
something to work with boom they're just
going to write the story and it's going
to be written in a way where you're
obviously going to get it mentioned so
yeah just dear report Roc calls are
really bad do you want to do a story on
it no that's just been done 17 times hey
here you know and then finding the new
ones right like recently we found
President Biden is telling you that you
won the Publishers Clearing House sweep
Stakes yeah no you haven't won that but
now we went that's a deep fake that's a
persuasion technique it's all these
other things that we've just gotten
better at that but what is that story
that is new and interesting and you can
give them some you have go to make their
job easy for them and then again when
you cut through the Clutter when they
know tell me what's new that was
honestly what was happening with a lot
of the reporters that we kept in touch
with hey next month tell me what's going
on so whenever there was also a gap when
like they didn't have a story going on
okay let's go back to Robo calls but
let's look at it what it's different
here and then it obviously the robo text
and the spam text and then any kind of
consumer protection those evolved from
that on the Apple and Google front did
Apple feature you out of the gate as one
of the early iOS 10 robocalling apps
yeah that was helpful from day one I was
never trying to be Shady right we're in
consumer protection so no tracking no
Shenanigans none of this like would we
just offer what we do so that also
worked with the Apple ethos so without
get into like the technical details
apple and privacy so an app developer
can't see calls that come into your
phone on our basic version we have to
load a block list and then Apple proxies
that so some people were like oh and
apple and we just have like no that's
the Privacy conscious way so when we
built ours you don't even have to give
us your phone number with our basic
product we do a better job if you do we
just basically rather than fighting we
slipstreamed hey this is how Apple wants
to do it we agree we love that that's
how we would want to be treated and then
when we were able to say you should
feature us as app of the day why because
we protect somebody and we're privacy
conscious that just became a competitive
advantage to us any other leverage
points that you feel over the years on
growth and user acquisition the best
thing that I'm thinking about on on
growth is we grew so slowly like it
might have gotten people really
frustrated to grow slow but the thing
about growth is it means that you're
getting better each day it's always the
dollars but in my mind it was how are we
growing value so the best I can say is
like yeah we grew slowly I guess if we
had maybe I don't know if there's a
parallel universe or I could invent a
time machine and go back in time and try
it again what would we have done if we
raised 10 or 20 or $50 million would
that have changed anything I don't
really know right you will never know
but I know that the path that I took was
growing at a sustainable pace and that
meant not overextending financially not
overextending hiring not biting off more
than we can chew until the right time so
I don't know if that's the right answer
but that's the way I looked at it that
leads us to the last topic I did want to
talk about today is that by approaching
it that way by being Scrappy by only
raising the money you actually needed by
not taking bad terms when you did need
the money but weren't going to get I
mean it's always that way with VC and
investors right it's like when you don't
need the money they'll give it to you in
great terms and when you do need the
money bad terms if you are on that track
and if you do think you might need money
do it before you need it because you're
just going to end up in a better
situation so you're growing you raise
money as needed you're Scrappy and then
you exit for over eight figures and to
spoil the story a little bit you own a
very big chunk so this is life-changing
money for you by making those Scrappy
decisions all along the way vers is
getting on that treadmill where you're
raising more and more and more money
owning less and less and less of the
outcome so tell me about the acquisition
like did you go out looking to get
acquired or at what point did you start
thinking like it's time to maybe exit
this business so on the acquisition side
we always had people knocking on our
door and like when you have a good app
when you have a good business people are
going to why are you knocking on and so
we got weekly a couple times a week
right and most of them were boilerplate
and most of them you just ignored and it
was noise and whatever we did a process
a few years back again like the
investors wanted a return and so okay
we'll go through that and we worked with
an investment banker and effectively all
the deals that we got we're just kind of
like lowball at that point we looked at
the numbers like this doesn't make any
sense like what they're offering is
where we're going to be so why would we
do that so we just kind of like okay
whatever I'm just making a ton of cash
right and so it's a great place to be
and we can then grow and hire and all
those and then yeah we got an inbound
offer from a pretty big company brought
to the board and we looked at it and we
you know where we going here and this
and that the other thing like maybe now
is the right time one of the lessons is
actually really important is to make
sure that two is one one is none so I
went back to all the other people that
and said hey look we're not running a
process but we got this offer because of
that we had our choice and we could have
gone with the big company and instead we
went with a smaller company that I felt
it was a better fit for the product the
timing was right the value was right and
again on the ownership side it worked
out I got a great return the employees
got a real good deal the investors got a
real good return the acquir if anything
I hope that this is the worst the
company ever is cuz just by putting on
there like just stuff that we just never
got around to it was an extra like a
terabyte directory that was just hanging
out in AWS we just didn't look at it
like I can't even imagine how much that
cost but it was like so those kinds of
things right and like I just keep on
joking I'm like now that you guys know
like what a terrible businessman I am
I'm I'm okay with that right it's like
it's fine just nobody understood why I
made certain decisions it was like I
only have a certain amount of resources
and I had to concentrate on what so if
right if that bucket cost I don't know
how much per month whatever I'll figure
it on out what's more important is when
the robocall blocking robocall industry
changed maybe two years ago right so new
technologies came out stir shaken the
carriers were stopping more and more of
these it could have blown up our entire
business I bet the business on our
product now it's called Max and it is
100% protection it has our block list it
has our allow list it has call screening
because now now it's is an unknown
number should I answer it and you don't
really know so looking at it from that
way like I got to build out Max great
Max is not two bucks a month it's five
bucks it's $50 a year there's a family
plan for 80 bucks a year there was just
way more value there and those are the
things people were screaming for on our
basic version hey can I protect my whole
family right listening to those people
building out Max and then saying look
this needs paid this needs people that
are experienced with this we could build
out this whole thing or is now the right
time and it yeah I would stayed here for
another decade or two doing exactly what
we were doing and it just made sense for
everybody and that's when you're kind of
in the driver seat too when you can say
no to something you're like uh no thank
you that's really what is I
unfortunately I see this so many times I
mentor and Coach a lot of startups and I
can't say this to them sometimes even if
they have like a just a disgusting cap
table like even if this works man this
isn't going to work you're putting in
all this effort and whatever and unless
it is like a trillion dollar company you
know maybe you'll walk away with a
million bucks I never wanted to get
myself into that jam I'm a very amateur
DJ and I love defining things with music
and things and so when the deal was
closing it was going about between 10
and 12 and I'm just sitting there
waiting but it was like I didn't know
what was happening or anything so I put
together a playlist and one of the songs
was closing time right we all know that
that's when it came up to that and then
right after that Frank snch was my way
and I was like you know what because I
took a very different path than
everybody else that I know and it took a
lot to listen to people and incorporate
that into my thinking I'm not saying I'm
perfect or right or anything like that
but to hear somebody who says again even
like on a board member right well you
should be doing this and then make it
your own and have a 10 year you're not
going to find the answer out for 10
years I just had to know that look this
is the way I'm wired and this is the way
it works and I think it's great and
that's why that song right just like I
did it my way and that song if you
listen to the lyrics it's when he's
towards the end of his life and he did
it his way and you know regrets had a
few but overall I think that's what been
great about this journey this story and
that's what I loved about it and so I
think hopefully your listeners will be
able to take from this yeah absolutely
it is such a great story and such a
great outcome and as someone super
bullish on this industry somebody had
apps I've had exits I've actually sold
three apps it's just such a cool
opportunity and it's a cool opportunity
that you didn't just go like exploit
people you're not like a scammy
subscription you brought value to people
over the course of a decade and made
life-changing money by doing that and
that speaks to the power of software and
Entrepreneurship and you know a lot of
people get in this like uh rich people
like they've worked on the backs of
others and stuff like that and there's
cases of that for sure where people get
rich not taking care of people not truly
bringing value into the world but
there's so many great entrepreneurs like
yourself and hopefully a lot of our
listeners as well that yeah make a ton
of money but make a ton of money
bringing a ton of value into the world
and that's the best way to do it like
the people are trying to scam their way
to the top the people are growth hacking
and other stuff it's like often those
are the ones that just flame out but
when your goal from the beginning when
you slow grow by bringing value to
people you just create better stuff and
better outcomes for yourself like the
line in the hip-hop s is a Tupac like I
made a g today yeah but you made it in a
sleazy way right just just drive Val you
I love the fact that we're talking now
cuz I've been reminiscing and looking
back and obviously had to put together a
bunch of stuff but for literally 10
years straight we had two to three press
mentions every single week for 10 years
straight wasn't paid or anything like
that either noar Robo or me or some like
10 years every single week on average we
were getting something and like yeah
that just doing it they say about
consistency for your listeners right
number one create value don't just make
tricks and dialing it in and
optimizations and everything number one
is value and number two is just
consistency I know it sounds so cheesy
but like those are really hard to do so
many people just create things that just
don't have they're cool okay cool and
that's great right and use those on side
projects and I'm not saying no to that
but if you're looking to have a business
the business has to create value the
value is reflected in money it has to be
because that's how we keep score in this
game and the more value you create like
again if it was robocalls block I'd have
like billion dollars I'm not
exaggerating we block billions of rooc
calls but obviously doesn't equal that
way but yeah the stuff is a very very
long road and it takes a lot but build
value and do things consistently and
you're already halfway there well I
think that's a fantastic place to wrap
up you've exited and you're going to be
moving on soon so you're not hiring or
anything else but anything else you want
to say as we wrap up yeah you know what
the biggest request that I would have is
I would love to talk to Founders that
are like me the Indie developers small
teams just reach out to me right like
what are the problems there that I can
help solve or what are the problems that
you're seeing or how can we solve these
things together because people keep on
asking me like what are you going to do
next and my answer is like whatever I
want and like what do I want to do is I
want to help people like me get to this
place so I was at Tech Stars foundercon
one year and I don't remember it was a
Founder that was telling the story and I
don't remember the details but his
company got Acquired and he had reached
the Mountaintop you know we're all
sitting around like what's it like he's
like you know what's up here
nothing I went I thought like okay so
I've gotten to the mountain I right got
the I had an idea built it up and it was
acquired that's the life cycle and this
is great and I got to the mountain toop
and it's great it's amazing the grass is
soft the air is so clean and there's
like lots of bunnies that run over and
they jump up and they're nice and fuzzy
I'm like it is so cool up here what I
want is to bring more people to that
mountain top I'm not investing there's
way more people that can do that way
better than me and you can get money
from anywhere right I do a lot of
mentoring and things but like what are
these pieces that people like us need to
get over to that next level to move on
to have their companies grow onto the
next one and graduate and things like
that so I would love to talk to anybody
yeah my email is just mearon f.com drop
it it's my personal love to talk to
people and see if there's anything that
we can do together that's my goal here
now now that I had a lot of people help
me up that mountain and now I'm going to
be helping a lot of people up that
mountain that is amazing I think you're
the first guest who's ever offered to
just help thank you so much for joining
it was just such a fantastic story and
thanks again for offering to help our
listeners and I hope people take
advantage of that pleasure and thank you
for having this podcast and you're
helping out everybody on this end right
anybody who's listening to this all the
value that you've been creating and
giving away how many lives view change
there so if we can go help out together
that's really the goal here and thank
you so much for this
time thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private
[Music]
community